good morning welcome to your meditating
with chair Vicky I'm a cognitive
psychologist and a cognitive scientists
at the University of Toronto we're in an
academic and scientific fashion I study
mindfulness related phenomena like
Insight flow mystical experience
transformative experience higher states
of consciousness enlightenment in the
cultivation of wisdom I've also been
practicing the past of meditation
met a contemplation touch each one she
come for over 29 years and teaching them
professionally for almost 20 years
welcome this is a course if you joined
us for the first time you're welcome to
stay but you should know this is of
course everybody Monday is a dharma day
and on that day I will teach a new
principle a new aspect of the practice
and it it progressively builds so if you
don't look at the description for this
video you'll find links to previous
lessons in two previous suits so that
you can catch up at your own leisure
Tuesdays through Fridays we sit and I
sometimes review what I taught on the
Dharma day at the end of every day
Monday through Friday
there's a Q&A but please keep any
questions you might have focused on this
practice practice and I'm teaching you
or the practices that I'm teaching it
for broader questions about how this
fits into a way of life or comparisons
between this practice and other
meditation practices or Buddhism in
general and stoicism or neoplatonism or
the general issue that's going on around
it what I call the meeting crisis in our
society please take those questions to
our monthly Q&A we live stream every
third Friday of the month 3 p.m. EST a
live stream is your name so please
remember to point other people to this
course if you get a chance because this
is one of the ways in which I'm trying
to help people with what's going on
right now and so you can help me help
others all right I think that's it for
morning announcements
and I'm glad that we're all making it
here together doing this practice is one
of the most powerful ways you can
befriend yourself so get comfortable
make sure to set your phones on do not
disturb and we will begin together when
I say begin
gravity consciousness and cutting
remember coming out of your suit is an
important part of the practice
we did people come out that they're here
to come out of the practice so say no
yeah slowly begin to come out of your
practice trying as best you can to
innovate what you cultivated here
practice with your everyday
consciousness and cognition
remember how you come out of your sit as
part of your practice sorry for that bit
of disruption there there was a
technical problem but it's been resolved
alright we have time for a few questions
this is from Andre there are when I'm
going through the five stages of the new
practice I'm supposed to use self
talking example I notice there's a pain
in my shoulder i reframe it as painting
and so to ask what does my body into
mine do and then I'm supposed to answer
these questions I'm asking to feel like
I could really easily get any stuck in
overanalyzing over stuck in my thinking
mind so you do need to do the inner
coaching and that might need some inner
speech as I said but tree gutters the
raft think about the fact that suppose
you're driving along and you notice
you're a gas you don't have to actually
say to yourself oh I might have gas you
can just notice it or you come into the
kitchen and you notice that one of the
chairs is not not that you might say
that to yourself but you you say that
because you already noticed or think of
all of the things that babies and small
children are capable of learning before
they can talk to themselves okay so you
have a tremendous capacity so use what
inner coaching you need but try to keep
it to a minimum maybe just you know
maybe just say you know in a body heart
mind and then try not to verbalize any
answers just try to see what new thing
comes up in your awareness as you
articulate those so what you have to do
the inner coaching so there's some inner
speech but you're trying to minimize it
you're trying to gradually reduce and
reduce it so you don't need it all and
you don't answer verbally you answer
observational you answer by seeing what
is revealed by you
actually directing your attention that
way but eventually you'll be able to
write intentionally direct your intent
your attention like you do what you're
doing right now without having to speak
to yourself you're not saying oh look at
the TV screen okay so yes but you right
from the very beginning you use frame
this says I'm using this as minimally as
I can in order to do the practice and I
am not generating verbal responses I'm
generating observational attention what
comes out what is new what do I see
because of it
next is Herman Ballack re what are the
similarities and differences between
flow and the past metal as we practice
them here so I'm not sure if you when
you're referring to flow you're talking
about finding your flow or you talk
about the flow phenomena in general I
would say the flow phenomena in general
is a state that people universally can
get into when there's a bunch of
characteristics met when the demands of
the situation slightly exceed people's
skills when there is clear and tightly
coupled feedback and when error makes a
difference and we're trying when we're
trying to find flow in our breathing
what we're doing is trying to set up
those kinds of conditions so we get into
a flow state because the closed state is
one of optimal attention absorption and
engagement is how we get coupled
interesa how we get coupled in a dynamic
fashion to an unfolding reality we want
to cultivate that skill so we can bring
it into our life in general so in
general the pass on ax is much more
focused on coordinating a kind of
attention especially the attention of
stepping back and looking at sensations
so I would say that the flow state is a
state that you can get into
independently of any training in the
past no but shixin moja has also
produced evidence that if you have a
training in a meditative practice like
the pasta it is conducive to flow I
think because of my Tai Chi Chuan
experience that flow is all
so conducive for meditative practices
like for Passover
Lars Karl how do you decide what to
meditate on in each session the pasta
meta and hiring mindfulness to decide
spontaneously or plan ahead I recommend
scheduling I recommend remember you
always do some capacitive no matter
which it in a start but I recommend
having a day overpass not a day of meta
perhaps one day a week doing the
meditative question the meditative
questioning to train vigilance but the
inquiring mindfulness should be
practiced whenever distraction
spontaneously arise no matter what
you're doing but pass the meta or the
question Norman Lorraine I've missed
many sessions trying to catch up is the
material in text form somewhere the
material isn't in text form it is but
we're in the process Kristin master
Pietro and I of rewriting the the
meditation manual on meditation and
contemplation that accompanies this
course I'd written one but it's its
oldest from like 1999 it's undergoing
serious revision and I'm hoping that
will be ready in a month or so I'm sorry
that might not help you write that much
but it is work in progress nimesh are
how do I overcome the frustration that
comes when the stream freezes because of
no internet on Maya and I have to guess
that what you say next so just note the
frustration frustrating but that's what
you're doing and then apply the five
factors of acquiring mindfulness and see
what opens up see what's there in that
and see if you can find something in
that there is capable of feeding back
into the purpose some kind of learning
as you open up inquiring mind fulness in
the frustration that you can befriend
crema can you give an example of using
the five factors of mindfulness on a
thought and one use it any time of day
not just and designated sit my narrator
needs eliminating well don't try and
eliminate your narrator
you need your narrator your narrator is
what gives you the capacity of being an
extend a temporally extended agent in
the world so the point is not to
eliminate we do not try to demonize or
deify any faculty that we have all of
our faculties can be friends all of our
faculties can be enemies what we try to
do is cultivate wisdom right Aristotle
was said this really beautifully about
anger he said the point is not being
angry or not angry it's knowing how to
be angry at the right time for the right
reason to the right degree it's
ultimately about making our actions and
our you know actions and our conceptions
optimally appropriate as possible this
is the core of wisdom I think it
ultimately has to do with the phenomenon
I study called relevance realization so
you can do what's called the thought
fast though I've done it a couple times
what you can do is throughout the day
whenever thinking comes up so thought
comes up I try not to get involved the
content I look at the voice is the voice
fast is it my voice is there one voice
is there multiple voices is the voice
sort of filled with emotion is it empty
of emotion does it seem to be very small
inside me or does it seem to be
surrounding me like the voice of God
coming from above or from without does
it carry Authority or is it more sort of
you know very passive or perhaps even
kind of you know we essent I try to pick
up on everything I can and as I keep
doing that the thoughts tend to to fade
away they fade away I try to know what
it's like when the thought is gone
that's the thought fast you're fast in
from thoughts so that that's basically
how you try and make use of this
practice second question from Andrew
here since the spring is finally here so
are my allergies they need advice on
what to do when I need to blow one's
nose and other allergy related need
comes up mid Rudy or practice in general
yeah I mean blow your nose sorry it you
don't want your air passageway to be
so that's kind of a disruption that if
you're honestly can't breathe through
your nose and you need to blow your nose
because you're not getting enough here
that you want employ your dose but if
you want to try breathing through your
mouth because your nose keeps stuffing
up now what you do is you putting it wet
your tongue and put your tongue on your
palate where you would say it's like dog
and then breathe and feel the air going
over your tongue and kind of keep your
tongue as moist as possible because that
way you could moisten the air coming in
and still get to any breathing cipriani
you said yesterday I think that you want
to avoid empty contentedness from
meditating what's problematic about
feeling content well it has to go with
what I said earlier
the goal of this practice is not to
achieve contentedness because very often
contentedness is not appropriate
so instead what's being sawn up there's
not a sense of connected contentedness
but what's called equanimity equanimity
is the ability to remain centered and
rooted and flowing in a situation
because you are appropriately in contact
with it you have that alter you have
that optimal appropriate sea of action
and conception and so we're not trying
to be content sometimes the appropriate
thing to be is to be as all set is to be
angry sometimes the appropriate thing to
be is to be sad right that the point is
again not to deify or demonize any state
or faculty but instead the thing that we
are trying to always optimize is
connectedness to ourselves to each other
and to the world okay so thank you
everyone for joining today thank you to
my good friend in techno major mark my
beloved son Jason they are always such a
big help please subscribe to this
channel to be notified of videos and
also the general Q&A
you'll also find on my channel a lot of
resources where I talk at length about a
lot of things we're talking about here
mindfulness meditation contemplation
flow inside mystical experience higher
states of consciousness the meeting
crisis how to cultivate with
somehow to cultivate deeper meaning in
life please invite others who might
benefit from this practice to join this
this group I'm trying to help as many
people as I can so I ask for your help
in helping as many people as our hand
reminder we do this every weekday Monday
to Fridays Monday is Dharma day Tuesday
through Friday our sit staves we do this
every weekday morning 9:30 est so I look
forward to seeing you all on Monday
Monday is Dharma T and we're going to
start we're going to talk about the
practice of integrity
so remember continuity of practice more
important than quantity of practice and
there is no enemy worse than your own
mind but there is no ally or friend
greater than your own mind take care of
everyone I'll see you guys on Monday bye
bye